Hello, community. So, great that you are
back. Let's talk about a new
mathematical filtration matrix because
we have now a new paper that tells us
student AI's are destroyed if you do
here a self-distillation.
So, this means if you have a small local
AI model on your PC, laptop, on your
computer infrastructure,
self-distillation fails. And this is now
a new insight we had not had before. And
if you're not familiar, the idea is
simple, no? You have I don't know, let's
go with Qwen-3 a 4-billion model, no?
And then you just make a copy, you clone
it here, and you provide the solution to
a particular set of your task in your
domain where you know the solution and
you want that the system simply learns
here new paths here.
So, this Qwen-3-4B will now access here
all the inside and learning paths here
from this Qwen that also has here the
golden solutions and knows exactly and
can validate it, let's say, in physics
or mathematics or whatsoever. So, highly
specific, domain-specific learning.
And this fails. And you might say,
"No, this is not true. The
self-distillation worked great, no?"
Well, let's have a look at this study.
July 2nd, 2026, here we have
from Zhejiang University, DAMO Academy
Lab from Alibaba Group, Wang Shang
University of Science and Technology,
Nanyang Technological University. And
honestly, I had no idea, so I asked
ChatGPT, "Hey, can you just print a map
and show me where those universities and
where Alibaba Group is?" So, now, okay,
this is China and here we have it.
This is here near Wuhan, Hubei. Oh, this
is here up in the north, interesting,
Jilin here. Automotive, artificial
intelligence, beautiful, engineering,
computer science. Zhejiang University,
nice. Okay. So, what they found is
amazing. We have a benchmark AIM 24, and
this is AIM 25. And the accuracy here
you see on the Y axis. And now we have
four models secure and 38B, a 4B, an
open a deep seek R1 distilled to 7B and
an almost 7B. And look at here the aim
25 accuracy in percentage with more
training step, it goes down. It loses
performance. All models lose performance
here in a self-diffusion task. And then
on-policy self-diffusion task. And you
may say, "How is this possible? This
model is supposed to learn, yeah?"
Because it's provided here the correct
solution path forward to your particular
solution.
So, we said, "Unbelievable." So,
on-policy self-distillation is not
working. But we thought it is working.
So, what is happening? And now the
beauty of this paper is that the authors
examined this. And let me show you why
it was so difficult. Now, they have a
hypothesis. The privileged teacher AI
with the golden solution, having seen
here what they call the reference
solution, has no need to reflect or
explore now on, "Hey, how could I find
the best reasoning path?" So, its
guidance now leans on, "Hey, I know the
answer. I know where this whole will end
up." Rather than, "Ah, look here. What
is the reasoning path and what you are
actually missing, my little other
student AI model." So, this means
the student AI inherits now only the
shortcuts instead of learning here the
skill of reasoning this particular task.
This is not what you want. And you may
say, "You know what? This is more or
less exactly the same like we
encountered here in medical AI." And I
showed you here in this particular video
just days ago, we have here maybe the
right answer that are remembered from
some textbook cases, but without the
correct reasoning. And this is something
you do not want to have in your hospital
or your clinic or your medical AI,
wherever you are, that maybe you get
your right answer, but anything that is
not textbook difficulty or complexity,
the system will fail in the reasoning.
So, this is highly dangerous. So,
therefore,
why? Now, we already have here
publication from end of May 2026, and
this is by Microsoft case and Seoul
National University, and they have,
"Hey, does self-distillation degrade the
reasoning capability of LLMs?" So, we do
have here some clear indication
something is going wrong. Especially if
you have your local model and you try to
do this you self-distilled you. You
wanted to increase the performance of
your local model, you actually failed.
Now, let's have a closer look why.
They decided to go for epistemic marker
analysis during the training here on a
mathematical chain of sort 20,000
training set.
So, we have here two models. First is a
Qwen-3-8B,
and then we have a DeepSeek-R-1-7B.
So, comparable sizes. Now, look at this.
Epistemic marker word are data, but
particular logic here that are happening
now.
Here, a count of thousand. Here, in
blue, you have the base model for the
specific term weight. And you know, in
the reasoning trace, you suddenly
suddenly see here that I don't know a
Qwen says, "Hey, wait. Let me
reformulate this. Or let me rethink
this. Or like wait, let's go back and
validate this claim." So, they just
counted here, "Okay, here we have 25,000
times the word weight is in the base
model.
Now, in the classical self-diffusion
standard, weight is
less.
This is about 10,000 times.
So, you see, if you look here at the
training step at Epis token count, you
see it is going down.
Now, look at this model here,
DeepSeek-R-1. We see the exact opposite
behavior.
We start here real close at 70,000, here
also at 70,000.
But then we go up to 110, 120,000.
Look, the base model is you still at 30,
I don't know, 30-something thousand of
weight.
But look, this new standard learned the
student AI now 80,000 times weight. And
it learned this that it really is 83,000
times the word weight is concatenated in
the output right next to the last
weight.
So you see something is horribly wrong.
Why is there this difference between the
model? The paper does not really explain
it in detail, but just notice this is
the behavior you're going to encounter.
And you say, "Okay, this is first
indication." So the authors of today's
paper said, "Hmm, can we have any way a
further deep dive into the over OPS D
supervision itself? Can we, you know,
separate some complexity, put it apart?
So we have here an understanding, a
mechanical understanding. Can we
decompose the complexity at least at the
level two?"
And they did it.
So they said, "Okay, we have an idea. We
construct a reference only teacher model
with a prior reference. Define us the
same model or 3B or 4B or 8B model.
Only now that the reference solution or
the result, the reference, is there now
without the question.
And this enables us to decompose the
teacher total update relative to the
current pi theta into two components.
So what they did was simple idea. Now
they said, "Okay, so we have here our pi
teacher and our pi theta.
And now
let's separate this in at least two
pieces. So we have our delta reference
and our delta inference transferable.
Not IT as information technology, but IT
is inference transferable.
This reference induced term will be the
term that is pure memorization.
There's no reasoning, there's no
learning, it just memorizes this.
This gives you the correct answer, but
this term would be here the reasoning.
This would be here the intelligent term,
the second one, the delta IT.
This would be where the student AI
learns now from the teacher AI with the
golden solution exactly how to reason.
And I said, "Okay, we are able to do
this mathematically, we split it up, and
now we analyze these two parameters in
the real world tests."
So,
just to be clear, the reference induced
signal delta ref captures the
supervision driven purely by the
reference solution. So, this is
information the student will never have
access to during the inference.
And the remaining inference transferable
signal, our delta IT, could capture now
the supervision that depends only on the
understanding of the problem, and would
remain useful at inference time when no
further reference is available.
Now, what is intended, what would be
here what we expect, is that our delta
total should align primarily with our
delta IT, no? The pure reasoning, the
crystallized reasoning traces.
If it is, however, memorizing here the
reference the solution, the golden
solution, it would align with delta
reference. So, let's test this out.
And here you have now the result of the
tests of this paper.
So, we have again two models. We have on
the left side the QN38B, and on the
right side here the DeepSeek R17B.
And we go for two different uh matrixes.
The cosine similarity is here the first
one given the training step, and the
norm fraction
on the training step. So, let's have a
look because there's a particular
interpretation of this. Let's go let's
say only with TQ run on the left side,
yeah?
Okay.
On both models we have a cosine of a
delta total and delta ref that remains
high throughout the training. This is
here the red line that you see.
So, the cosine similarity here of those
two deltas is really high. Confirming
now that the teacher persistently pulls
the students towards the reference
rather than towards the question
condition real reasoning.
So, you see here
this is here exactly what you do not
want to have. But, this is exactly what
we found.
Now, the other two, image two and four
if you want here, is now about norm
fraction plots.
You see here
this is the norm of delta ref to delta
total consistently exceeds one. You see
here here's the one line and this are
here the indicators where here at one
point, I don't know, 1.2 plus 1.3, and
then we come close to 1.0 again at 200
training steps.
So, this means this
specific parameter here, the red curve,
exceeds one, meaning now that the
reference induced component is larger
than the total update itself. So, this
reference, the solution-orientated
shortcut, dominates now the learning
process.
So, the inference transferable component
practically cancel
itself out rather than reinforcing it.
So, this is now some devastating result.
This is now something
that explains why we are not having a uh
self-distillation here of small models.
Okay, but there's a second point to
this. Now, let's look again at this. So,
the inference transferable signal
partially recovers as reference
memorization saturates. So,
on a Q and 38B, let's say let's go here.
Our cosine of the delta total to delta
IT, this is here our green line,
rises from let's say about minus one or
minus 0.95 to almost zero. So, this is
the cosine similarity cosine from zero
you know what it is. On the other model
here,
you have here the cosine of delta total
to delta ref, not the red one, rapidly
climbs from 0.6 to let's say one, almost
one, 100% in the first 100 steps and
then it plateaus out.
So, this pattern is now consistent with
the interpretation that the reference
induced component being quickly
memorized during the training.
And as the student absorbs here the
reference signal,
the update along our delta ref
diminishes and the residual delta IT
becomes relatively more visible.
This gives us here now, according to the
authors and explanation, why we have an
OPSD failure, why we cannot self-distill
smaller models from each other.
Because if you go for a long chain of
short models, for a reasoning models,
for complex queries, this is caused by
the dominance of the reference induced
supervision, our delta reference from
the golden rule, the shortcut if you
want, over the inference transferable
supervision, our delta IT, the real
reasoning,
in the teacher update signal. So, if you
split the teacher update signal into
those metric analysis, you see, okay,
there's no reasoning signal at all
because the reasoning of the teacher is
taking the shortcut since the teacher
model knows the solution.
This is the reason why this training
fails.
And you say, "Damn,
what can we do about it?"
Because this actually mean that the
teacher AI was mathematically poisoning
the student AI to just memorize the
answer, but never giving it really the
complete reasoning trajectory. Only the
shortcut because it knew the answer.
And now the student AI simply fails in
learning and does not learn anything at
all. It overrides its own knowledge and
it is a catastrophe for a student AI.
Now, remember I had an old other videos
here 3 days ago, really old videos,
where I showed you you can do this here
in the natural language.
That we have then a read out here of the
logic and we say, "Okay, this is our
vocabulary." Now we have here a
beautiful English sentence as an output.
This is not the case in this particular
video. Here in this video we go for the
real mathematical probability tensors.
We do not convert it to a human language
at all. We stay with our two LLMs here
at the absolute mathematical abstraction
of a tensor, of a probability
distribution for each single token.
So, because the supervision happens via
the massive probability tensors across
the entire vocabulary, you cannot easily
debug the teacher's feedback just by
reading it.
And the authors tell us, "This is
precisely why the standard OPSTD was
failing silently and nobody understood
why or it was not even communicated that
it is not working at all."
And the authors said, "Great. Now that
we have the insight why it is not
working, we can go the next step and
find a solution and improve it." And
this is always the case when you find
something not working, you want to
improve it, make it better.
The authors start, "Our decomposition
identifies here delta as the
non-transferable component of the
teacher supervision, so the residual,
this is not a difference of a log pi pi
teacher minus the log of pi reference,
this is the residual, the delta IT
is now obtained by subtracting this
reference and use component and can be
interpreted as a conditional PMI style
residual.
So, this means if you're not familiar
with information theory,
this
signal delta IT is the pure golden
advice. This is the reasoning that we
want. Since the teacher only does say
and mean a reason because of the
obstacles that it found and the solution
that it has to develop. In information
theory, this leftover signal, this
residual signal is called in general in
information theory a pointwise mutual
information, a PMI.
It is the purified lesson of the
learning exercise.
So, we go now with a little bit of
information theory.
However,
and now we come to a mathematical
problem that you will immediately
identify,
the delta IT is a per token log
probability difference
and not at all a distribution that
student DI can directly learn from.
So, how the hell do we go from a log
probability difference representation of
some data complexity into a distribution
that the student needs to learn because
guess what, we have probability
distribution logic, self-attention, you
know all of this thing.
So, the authors have now a beautiful
mathematical idea.
And they say, we use not the classical
pointwise mutual information, the PMI,
and there are some papers, please have a
look at the papers 20 1999 and 2014,
and they have a mathematical mechanism
to convert this residual into a
well-formed target distribution.
And here some steps, 1 2 3 4 steps, and
they achieve here the formula five.
Our P PMI.
Now you will say, "Hey, wait a minute.
This exact closed form this
this resembles here something that we
learned here in my video as a subscriber
of my channel here from reinforcement
learning." Yes, of course. Look at this.
This is an exact closed form. You take
the honest baseline, you multiply by an
exponential of the rescaled reward
function, and then you just re-normalize
here or normalize here with a particular
constant, yeah?
And you say, "Wait, I know this idea
from It's It's not in the paper, but you
know it, yeah?"
You know that this is exactly more or
less from GRPO some of the mathematical
let's call it trick optimizations
from from reinforcement learning.
And we The authors now applied this
exactly here
multiply with the exponential of the of
the rescaled reward function. And this
is our delta IT.
What a nice idea.
But now of course they had the problem,
hey, can we really
have here the fixed token position
that's the transferable reward of
choosing the vocabulary item V easier
than feared inference transferable
residual, and is this really a closed
form an optimal distribution under a
cool back lever regularized distillation
objective?
And they just go through some steps and
they show you, yes, look, this is
exactly equation five.
What we came up with. This is exactly
where we started.
So yeah, this is now really an exact
closed form.
So,
I would say this is a
how to call this an an innovation
transplant here from reinforcement
learning now here to self-distillation.
But what a nice idea. A little bit of a
complex mathematics, but in general it
is this in I would call it here the same
idea. Maybe there are some deeper
understanding I have not just yet got
it. It's just 2 days ago that I got the
paper, but I think really nice. Have a
look at this.
So, once you can isolate now the
residual, there's one snack. Now, as I
told you, it's just the difference
between two log probability, you know?
Any real number doesn't sum to anything
sensible across the vocabulary, so you
can't hand it to a divergent loss
directly, a loss function, you know?
So, they fix, as I told you, some
closed-form trick, at least in my
interpretation. Maybe I'm wrong. Please
correct me in the comments. Is DPO and
reinforcement learning by human feedback
free to residual as a per-token reward.
Mathematically, optimization is the late
maximum reward while staying close in a
Kullback-Leibler sense to the model's
own honest question only distribution
has the exact closed-form trick to our
honest baseline multiplied by an
exponential of the rescaled reward and
renormalize everything we do normally
here in RL. Beautiful.
If we have achieved this one more of
five, now we can go to the training.
Let's train this model. Now, since we
have this new idea, let's do this.
So, the final loss function here, loss
hours, quotation mark by the authors,
replace now the privileged teacher here
with our PMI target.
And you say, "Hey, wait a minute. This
target is what?" Well, the practical
target distribution is formed by adding
here the stabilized PMI signal to the
base model log probabilities and
normalizing it again. So, here is
exactly the term that we were missing
here.
You look at this and say, "Hey, yeah,
Shannon, beautiful.
Everything is known, you know?"
Wait a minute.
In a standard OPST, which distills from
here pi
teacher, and therefore inherits here the
reference induced shortcuts,
our objective now distills, or just
tells us, only the question-conditioned
correction
while keeping the student anchored to
its clean base reasoning prior.
So, they have now a mathematical
filtration tensor
filtering out everything that is not the
question condition correction.
So, everything that was more or less
here with the reference or the solution
based inside.
And now we have we we we hope we can
trust here this mathematical filtration
methodology.
Because then we get here the pure golden
reasoning traces that we need now really
for the self-distillation.
And now let's fingers crossed that this
self-distillation will work.
Now, I know I have some of my viewers
that say, "Hey, this is all so simple
and so easy.
But, tell me how we go from this simple
trivial idea to coding this?" And I
think that's a beautiful idea. So, let's
have a look at the mathematics at the
details. Because guess what? You'd code
this mathematical detail. This is where
the code comes from and not from Claude
code.
Okay.
Let's have a look at the If you want,
you can skip this, but it's really
interesting. The concrete computational
procedure for constructing now a
stabilized PMI target at each specific
token position T.
Think about it. What do we have to do?
We need three forward passes through the
same frozen base model pi zero, let's
call it zero,
differing only in the input prompts plus
the student's own forward pass. Then,
someone say, "Hey, wow, we increase
threefold." No, not at all. This is the
beauty of this mathematical solution.
Stage one.
All easy generation in the forward pass.
So, the student generates the
trajectory. This is Y hat, let's call it
this, and we obtain a three set of logic
over the full vocabulary at each
position T. Why?
You remember we had the teacher our
reference in the base model. So, we have
the teacher.
The teacher has access to the question
and the golden solution the reference.
Beautiful. This is here our teacher L
sub teacher.
The reference probe is L sub reference.
This is here where we have the reference
only.
And then we have the base model. This
has the question only.
So and with these three elements now
we run it and we have simply we compare
it and we filter the difference out.
That's all.
So this means we take the next
uh exact same frozen model have it
predict the next token give them only
the reference answer with the question
hidden. Whatever it confidently predict
under the condition is by construction
the information that has nothing to do
with understanding the question and
reasoning about the question because we
have the solution we have the reference
answer and therefore we don't have to
think with our human brains or with the
AI brains. Beautiful. So therefore
subtract that from what the real
privilege teacher says and the residual
is the part of the teacher guidance that
hopefully only exists because of the
question was there and not because of
the knowledge of the solution.
Could not be simpler. No, we already had
this. This is simply here you subtract
this reference part from the complete
complexity of the teacher inside.
So this is how you complete the raw PMI
signal.
Yeah, softmax of L of our L, clear.
And then we have to do a little bit of
centering. This is just here something
think about here just to have here that
the correction numerical becomes stable.
So the PMI becomes now a stable
mathematical solution. This is a
mathematical trick if you want. But then
we have to do a soft clipping, yeah?
Because to uh we apply a tangent
hyperbolic space soft clipping to bound
the extreme PMI values while preserving
the direction and the relative ordering
of them
values here and the clipping here and
there case they found that 10 is here
the perfect numerical value for the soft
clipping. Beautiful.
And then we have to construct you now
the stabilized PMI target.
And here we have our beautiful softmax
formula again, and our beta beta that we
set here as a kind of a hyperparameter
to one. So, we have to full correction
here.
And again, this is our delta IT that we
have here.
So, this practical target distribution
is formed by adding now the stabilized
PMI signal to the base model log
probabilities and normalized it. So, you
see this is all that we were interested
in, no?
Here we have it, our stabilized PMI
target. Here we have the base model, and
then we just add here our delta IT term
where we are sure that there is nothing
from the golden solution
highjacking here the reasoning trace of
the teacher model.
And we just add it, and then we have our
softmax function. I mean, if you look at
this, you say, "Hey, it's so simple to
code this now." But, you have to make
sure on a mathematical level that it is
stable, that it is convergent, that it
is not going crazy in some particular
area of the mathematical space. So, if
you do this without mathematics,
you can have some surprises, and this
will not work at all. So, yeah, it's
better that you studied a little bit of
mathematics, let's say four to six
semesters of mathematics at the
university to have a little bit of a
feeling if this is a stable solution,
and the log is of course this.
And then we are finally able at step six
to have here the training loss itself.
So,
P target is defined here, beautiful. So,
the student is updating here
by minimizing the generalized
Jensen-Shannon divergence, our JSD,
between the student distribution and the
stabilized PMI target. That's it.
And you would say, "Yeah, simple, nice."
I know, but you know what? The most
powerful ideas are sometimes simple if
you really understand it.
Yeah, let's come back to the
computational effort. Yes, absolutely,
you're right, no? Compared to your
standard OPS the other method required
two additional forward passes per
training step. Imagine, yeah, this is
huge, but
they forward passes differ only in the
input prompts, so they are based on the
same already generated trajectory and do
not require any back propagation. You
know what this means? The authors tested
this out how much more computation we
have to do and they found out with all
this new less than 10% compared to the
original implementation.
This is great. This is beautiful. Less
than 10% more compute for
self-distillation that suddenly works.
I take it.
Okay, after this, let's come to the
results. Let's have a look.
Different two different benchmark M24,
M25, whatever you have, average one,
average two, great.
So, we go now for four models and for
all four models they give us three
methodology, the base classical, the
standard OPS that more or less fails
here. You see it's even below here the
base model, so this is not a good
indication. If the base model here has
.8 and the new OPS, the self-distilled
has 75.4, this is not where you want to
go.
But this new brand new OPS DPMI hours is
of course, oh yeah,
hardly hardly
four percentage point better, but at
least it is an increase. It is improving
here than before.
And you see everything is bold, bold,
bold, bold, so it compares here.
It supersedes here every other
methodology. Great on a 8B, 4B as a
distilled 1.7 B and almost 7B.
So, it works crossover the models
tested.
Nice.
Now, since we see that it is not really
jumping here another 10 percentage point
or maybe 20 percentage point, it tells
us something, no?
Maybe the separation that the authors
state in their simplest um assumption
here at the very beginning of the paper,
no?
Maybe this has to be done in a little
bit more mathematically advanced way.
Maybe a simple separation had "Hey, this
is your report. It belongs here to This
comes from the solution inside and then
the rest that leaves we leave behind
must be from the pure reasoning." Maybe
it's not that simple, but it is an
indication that tells us, "Hey, this is
working." So, this is the direction we
have to go.
Now, I want to show you now the training
dynamics on our math chain of sort
20,000 with AM 2025.
Again, here we have the 8B, 4B, 7B, and
the 7B all more.
And here we have it now. In red, we have
the standard and in green, get what?
This is the new our new methodology from
the paper here in green and you see
green is outperforming everything.
So,
it replaces now here this with its
purified PMI target and it remains
stable above the baseline dashed
throughout the training.
This is beautiful. This is exactly what
we wanted. We have to understand hey,
why is there a dip here, but otherwise,
yeah, everything looks great.
Now, this is now for me an open
question. Look at the epistemic marker
analysis here
and we have here in green now with
weight for the epistemic marker the word
weight.
Now, that green is really here more or
less identical to the blue marker. This
is the base model.
So, this is now the if you want the
finding here that
with the new model, the new PMI
alteration here in the algorithm, we
have more or less reached the base model
again, which is beautiful.
And you see, yeah, but you know, even
the classical standard here has here for
weight a better result.
Why have you not reached here the better
result with our new PMI methodology?
It is completely different if you look
here at C and D, our deep seek R1.
Here we have the complete different
curve, you see.
Here we have that now the base is in
blue and in green we have our new PMI.
And green is equal or almost equal here
to blue, beautiful.
And there we had that we had with our
standard self-distillation this horrible
83,000 times the word weight in the
answer.
And you don't want to have in your
answer 83,000 times the word weight.
So, here it is working.
Here
I'm not really sure that I understand
the difference. So, if you got it, if
you find a solution, please leave a
comment in the description of this
video. I would be highly interested to
find here an interpretation. Maybe I was
not clever enough to understand it,
maybe I over read it here. Hey, this is
here what we have to understand next in
the process, no?
Great.
Final.
The authors here, at the end the authors
always have the last words, we propose a
two-step solution. First, constructing a
reference only teacher, just clone it,
to isolate the non-transferable
component and reveal the question
conditioned residual.
Now we understand, maybe it is not as
easy as just say minus. Maybe this is
has to be a little bit more
mathematically filtered in a more
advanced mathematical
functional operational way.
And second, the authors tell us using
pointwise mutual information PMI as the
mechanism to anchor this residual onto
the base distribution, producing a
purified PMI target that the student can
directly distill from.
You you what is this? This is a mapping
here to a base manifold distribution.
And you see it is more or less always
the same idea that we have if we
implement new AI technology.
Remember the video where I showed you
this? Yes? No?
Okay.
Hope you had a little bit of fun, some
new information. It would be great to
see you in my next video.